立法會主席。
發言，石禮謙議員就政府帳目委員會第六十三A號報告書向本會發言，石禮謙議員。
Thank you, Mr. President. On behalf of the Public Accounts Committee, hereby known as the Committee, I have the honour to table our report number sixty-three A today. This report is supplemental to the Committee's report number sixty-three and contains our conclusions and recommendations.
Recommendations on Chapter Four of the Director's Audit Report Number 63.
on the administration of the air traffic control and related services.
香港是個國際和區域航空樞紐。
and the civil aviation department, the CAD, has an important role to provide a safe, reliable, effective and efficient air traffic control service.
The committee wishes to highlight that, for the purpose of protecting life and property, air safety must not be compromised under any circumstances. The committee's report looked into the irregularities in the director's of audit's report, in respect to.
Of the air traffic control and other related services, a total of six public hearings were held on this chapter.
五次聽證會是專門收集有關採購新空管系統（ATMS）的證據。
The committee also paid a visit to.
CAD。
to better understand the operation of the existing.
existing ATMS system and the testing of the new ATMS.
The committee finds it appalling and totally unacceptable that the existing air traffic control system
which, according to the administration, ought to have been retired by December 2012, due to the end of production of some components and its limited functionalities and capacities.
According to the audit report, the system have been operating above its planned capacity, and the frequency of surveillance data display problem has increased since 2011.
As at May two thousand and one, five, no new safe and reliable air traffic control system is in operation, and the latest estimate was that the new system would only be ready for operation in the first half of two thousand and six. This is mainly due to a delay.
在Implementation of the ATMS contract, which is one of the eight major contracts of the system.
now I shall touch on the subject of procurement of the new ATMS system. The committee strongly condemns CAD for its incompetence and negligence in managing the procurement and implementation of the ATMS project, which an original contract value of.
四百八十六萬。
Apart from the project being delayed for three and a half years, there are a number of irregularities found by the committee in the public hearings.
I briefly highlight the irregularities in three aspects. Firstly, contract variations. Two contract variations were made by CAD at a total cost of 89.2 million dollars. The committee is of the view that the sum items in these two variations.
應已由CAD預見。此情況是不理想的，因為第一次合約變更是在簽約後11個月才提出，而兩次合約變更是在17個月內進行。
第二，液化損害。
According to the new ATMS contract, the contractor was only required to pay up to a maximum of five million dollars as liquidated damages as a result of the delay in delivering the system in phase one of the contract. This is the commissioning of the new system. The
City has doubts on the effect of such clause as an incentive for the contractor to expedite the delivery of the new system, as the same contractor was paid around 5.9 million dollars a year for upgrading and maintenance work of the existing system.
over the last three and a half years.
第三，第三ly， tendering terms the new ATMS contract only requires the tenderers to provide a system with a minimum track record of not less than six months, but but this short track record might not fully reflect the capacity and performance of the new system.
to handle fluctuations in the air traffic due to seasonal changes.
In addition.
It is stipulated in the tender document that the proposed system, with no proven performance, will not be considered further.
According to CAD, the term system in inverted commas should mean a basket of system and subsystem, subsistence.
This interpretation, however, is not made known to tenderers or potential tenderers. It would be difficult, if not impossible, for any parties who are interested in submitting tender proposals, to be aware of such interpretation prior to the award of the contract.
The committee strongly condemns and deplores the director general of the civil aviation, as head of the civil aviation department, had blatantly failed to perform his duties and responsibilities in ensuring that due diligence relating to the ATMS.
contract was conducted adequately and thoroughly. The conditions of the contract was set up clearly and appropriately, and the contract was implemented effectively, on schedule and in a cost-effective manner.
委員會進一步表達深切 concern，並認為不接受，即係交通及房屋局，作為監察民航局運作的局，未能履行其監察職責。
to ensure that an effective implementation of the new air traffic control system by civil aviation department.
作為立法會，立法會議決有憲制角色在批准公眾開支，而行政部門必須向立法會負責。委員會表達深切關注，也發現不接受THB和CAD。
未not reported to the relevant Legislative Council panel or the Finance Committee of the two contract variations of the ATMS contract, nor drawn members' attention to the substantial delay in the replacement of the air traffic control system in a timely manner, undermining the role of
This council in monitoring the government expenditure effectively.
The committee urges the civil aviation department should ensure that the existing air traffic control system is timely maintained in good operation conditions before the new system is commissioned in mid 2016.
CAD應 formulate a contingency plan in the case.
In case of a new safety and reliable air traffic management system could not be delivered by the first half of two thousand and sixteen or any other indicative date to be set by CAD and THB, CAD should also ensure that the new system is safe, reliable and.
stable to be used, and all deficiencies and observations identified must be completely and satisfactory resolved prior to putting the new system into operation.
The committee also urges that TAB, THB.
應該考慮engaging external and independent experts immediately to assess the safety and.
performance of the new ATMS system, as well as the likelihood of completing completing the first phase of the ATMS contract in the first half of 2016, and formulate a plan accordingly.
On the next subject, on the management of Precision Runway Monitor project, the committee expressed strong resentment that the Civil Aviation Department had failed in its responsibilities in ensuring public money spent on procuring a Precision Runway Monitor, hereby known as.
PRM。
This monitor radar at the cost of 101.4 million in 2000 in year 2000 was good value for money. The radar was intended to support the independent mixed mode of of operation of the Hong Kong International Airport's two runways. This
to allow each runway to function separately and without coordination with operations on the other runway.
如果這種運作模式可以被採納，它會最大化飛行線容量。而在此基礎上，FC批准了101.4萬。
However, the CAd was aware that there were constraints in adopting this mode of operation by two consultancy studies in the year 1900.
ninety and nine one nine nine and in the year nineteen hundred nineteen hundred and ninety four.
CAD still proceeded with the procurement of the PRM radar in the belief that there might be an advancement in technology to overcome such constraints in future.
Unfortunately, as such advancement never materialised, the PRM radar was put to a supplemental supplemental uses. It has subsequently been put into standby mode since 2005.
The committee also expressed strong resentment that the Civil Aviation Department did not inform the Public Works Committee or the Finance Committee in the funding application for the PRM radar in 1996.
about the constraint in adopting the independent mixed mode of operation and the implementation of which was contingent on advancement in technology.
The committee urges the civil aviation department should adopt a mechanism to ensure that the equipment purchase are cost-effective, and public money are not used are to be used in the prudent.
咩呢？
In addition, it should set out both the pros and cons of a proposed project, including all potential risks and relevant contingent factors, in the funding application to the Legislative Council for members to make an informed decision of whether to support the projects.
Lastly, I wish to record my appreciation of the contribution made by members of the PAC committee. Our gratitude also goes to the witnesses who attended the hearings, helped by the committee. I would like to express our gratitude to the Director of Audit and his colleagues for their unfailing support and.
Lastly, but not the least, this Secretariat of the Council. Thank you, Mr. President.
執出。
今日嘅會議咧，除咗六項。